Guide to the Herbert J. Gezork Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Herbert J. Gezork papers
1931-1981
RG 298
Yale University Divinity School Library
9
(22 boxes)
The Gezork papers document his professional career, including as Professor of Social Ethics and Christian World Relations at Andover Newton Theological School from 1939 to 1950 and President of Andover Newton from 1950 to 1965.
Gezork, Herbert Johannes, 1900-1984
Biographical / Historical
Herbert Johannes Gezork was born June 15, 1900, in Insterburg, Germany. He graduated from Baptist Divinity School in Hamburg and in 1925 became pastor of First Baptist Church in Berlin, where he was ordained on December 8, 1927. He did graduate study at the University of Berlin from 1925 to 1928 and continued his doctoral work in the in the United States at Southern Baptist Theological Seminary.
After receiving the Ph.D. degree at Southern Baptist in 1930, Gezork returned to Germany to become General Secretary of the German Baptist Youth Movement. He held that position until 1934, when the group was dissolved under Hitler's government because the Baptist organization was in direct opposition to the popular Hitler Youth organization. During this period he published two titles, both of which were banned by Hitler's government: an essay, "Unsere Jiingerschaft und unser Zeugendienst im Blick auf die Gottlosenbewegung" (1932) and a book, So Sah Ich die Welt (1933).
He escaped arrest by coming to the United States in 1936. Gezork became a citizen of this country in 1943. After World War II, he traveled to Europe on three different occasions on behalf of the U.S. government, twice for the Defense Department and once for the State Department.
Before his association with Andover Newton Theological School, Gezork taught at Furman University (1937-1938) and Wellesley College (1939-1943). He became Professor of Social Ethics and Christian World Relations at Andover Newton in 1939. In 1950 he became President, a position he held until his retirement in 1965.
He was an active preacher and lecturer in retirement. Herbert J. Gezork died October 21, 1984, in Vero Beach, Florida.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
From the Andover Newton Theological School Collection, transferred to the Yale Divinity Library in 2017.
Scope and Contents
The Herbert J. Gezork Papers, 1931-1981, document his professional work. The collection is arranged according to the following categories: sermons, prayers, addresses, lectures, literary manuscripts, class lectures/course documentation, student papers, and personal mementos related to his inauguration as President of Andover Newton and to his life and work in general. The bulk of the collection is comprised of material described as class lectures/course documentation.
Arrangement
Series I. Sermons
Series II. Prayers
Series III. Addresses
Series IV. Lectures
Series V. Literary Manuscripts
Series VI. Class Lectures/Course Documentation
Series VII. Student Papers
Series VIII. Personal Mementos.
Gezork, Herbert Johannes, 1900-1984; Andover Newton Theological School; Andover Newton Theological School
- Sermons, Series I
  - Sermons arranged by Biblical text (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    See list of texts in first folder of this series.
  - Sermons arranged by Biblical text (Box 2)
  - Sermons arranged by Biblical text (Box 3)
  - Sermons arranged by topic, using Gezork's categories (Box 3)
    Topics: Anxiety/faith; Authority/freedom; Beware; Calvary:then and now; Choices; Christ; The Christian and the world; The Christian faith in a world of crises; Christian families in the social and political revolution; A Christian looks at the Arab-Israeli conflict; Christian social responsibility; Christian witness in a revolutionary world; Church today; The Conquest of death; Detachment/involvement; An End and a beginning; Evangelizing in an age of crisis; Evil, suffering, and a good God; Faith, money and stewardship; Freedom; God is love; Gott ist Liebe; Human suffering and divine love; Involved in mankind; Learning and faith; Look backward -look forward -look upward; Lukas-Johannes (6 folders; includes both Gospel of John and epistle I John); Means and ends; Meeting the crisis in Christian leadership; Organization man; Organization man/God's man; Our Christian witness in an age of revolution; Palm Sunday Pentecost and renewal (2 folders)
  - Sermons arranged by topic (Box 4)
    Topics: Pilgrims and exiles; Prepare for temptation; Promises to keep; Reconciliation in a broken world; Religion in the technological revolution [Science, technology and faith]; Sermon on the mount; A Sense of urgency; The Surrender that is victory; That the light ... be not darkness; Tradition/renewal
  - Sermon abstracts and articles (Box 4)
  - Easter services, 1939-1942, 1943-1959, 1962-1964 (Box 4)
    Sermons from texts; Topical sermons; Prayers, etc.
- Prayers, Series II
  - Prayers (chronological), 1940-1949, 1950-1959, 1960-1969 (Box 4)
- Addresses, Series III
  - Chronologically arranged
    - Berlin, 1931 (Box 4)
    - I am grateful for America; What America means to me, 1939 (Box 4)
    - Be grateful for America, 1940 (Box 4)
    - ANTS opening; Be grateful for America; Bush not consumed, 1941 (Box 4)
    - Advent; Because we care!; Community chest, Boston; Newton Community Fund Drive; This is democracy; Voluntariness, 1943 (Box 4)
    - Work and worship, 1944 (Box 4)
    - The quest for a new sex morality; United War Fund; World Student Service Fund, 1945 (Box 4)
    - Andover Newton chapel, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Christmas; Community chest, 1948 (Box 4)
    - Anniversary banquet, 1950 (Box 4)
    - Idolatries, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Abraham; This I know, 1955 (Box 4)
    - The quest for Christian unity, 1957 (Box 4)
    - ANTS opening, 1958 (Box 4)
    - ANTS Baccalaureate; Charge to churches; The educational crisis (2 versions), 1959 (Box 5)
    - Fraternal greeting to Southern Baptist Convention; Surrendering all -- do we mean it?; Of true happiness - CBS Church of the Air, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Albert Schweitzer; Toyohiko Kagawa; The Challenge of our declining sense of values; Walter Rauschenbusch, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Brotherhood; Word and work of God, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Abraham, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Peace with justice, 1964 (Box 5)
    - American kaleidoscope; Between despair and hope; Of dubious relevance; Farewell dinner; W. L. Hills, 1965 (Box 5)
    - One mission; Our Christian witness in a revolutionary world (2 folders), 1967 (Box 5)
    - Europe; Political life, 1968 (Box 5)
    - Across the generation gap, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Installation of Bartlett Professor of Sacred Rhetoric; Perplexities and frustrations of the minister, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Chautauqua (2); God bless America, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Hunger; Israel, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Lest we forget, 1976 (Box 5)
    - How much is a college education worth?;You can take it with you, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Lent; Lord's Supper, 1978 (Box 5)
    - By bread, but not by bread alone, 1979
  - Undated sermons arranged by title
    - A - Christian Ethics (Box 5)
      Advance - retreat?; Age of revolutions; America, the hated and the loved; Areas and issues of Christian responsibility; Ash Wednesday (2 addresses); Baptists of the south and north should be close; Basic ideas of world conflict; The challenge of our declining sense of values; The Christian concept of sex and marriage; Christian ethics
    - Christian Faith - K (Box 6)
      Christian faith and political action; The Christian in politics; Christian unity; Christian witness in a world of change;Christianity behind the Iron Curtain; Christianity in Europe today; Christianity in Germany; Christianity - spiritual and material; Christians responsible; Christmas in Communist lands; Co-existence Commencement address; Community chest; Crisis; Crisis of belief; Crisis of society; The Cross; Death is not final;Decisions; The Deeper crisis; Democracy begins with you!; Education; Europe (2 addresses);Faith and learning; Family; Fourfold hunger of the world; A Free-for-all in morals; God; God: the subject; God's will?; Gott ist liebe; Greatness of a nation; Immortality; Is Christianity the answer?; Is ours a post-Christian age?; The Jerusalem of your soul; Judge not; Kingdom of God
    - L - Y (Box 7)
      Laymen; Marriage and religion; Marriage counsel; Martin Luther King; Masons; [Morality] (incomplete); Neither ghetto nor melting pot; New Delhi (2 versions); Our Baptist faith today; The personal revolution; Political responsibility; Problems of Christian home and family; Protestantism; Protestantism today; Religion and philosophy; Religion and politics; (2 versions); Religion in the university; Religious ethics and political responsibility; Report on Europe 1967; Romance, love, marriage; Sex, marriage, family; The state; Stranger in our midst; Students today; Thanksgiving (2 folders); This is democracy; This religious,pagan America; "To them gave he power"; What is right?; What is the American way of life?; What lies ahead for America?; Why did Jesus die?; Why give; The world's deepest hunger; Your future ministers
- Lectures, Series IV
  - Undated lectures, arranged by title
    - [Notes and fragments]; Campus Crusade for Christ: a polemic; Christian conscience and atomic war; Christian faith and moral decision; Christian faith and the technological revolution; Christian history; A Christian-Marxist dialogue?; The Cults; Materialism of Christianity; The Practice of religion in a technological culture; Religion is the opiate of the people; Technology (2 folders); Toward death or renewal? (Box 7)
  - Chronologically arranged
    At end of lectures arranged by date are 2 folders of clippings related to lecture topics
    - Hromadka - a critical interpretation of his position, 1954 (Box 7)
    - Religious faith and moral imperatives; Sex and chastity; Marriage and divorce, 1956 (Box 7)
      Also includes information and correspondence on the Lowell Institute lectures given by Gezork in 1956
    - The Evangelical academies in Germany, 1958 (Box 8)
    - Religion and the academic community, 1964 (Box 8)
    - The Biblical basis of the church; The Mission of the church; The Renewal of the church, 1965 (Box 8)
    - Building the church, 1966 (Box 8)
    - Our Christian witness in an age of revolution, 1967 (Box 8)
    - Situation-ethics, 1968 (Box 8)
    - Christian eschatology and the theology of hope, 1971 (Box 8)
    - Vaughan Dabney, 1973 (Box 8)
    - The American student today (3 versions), 1974 (Box 8)
    - The Baptist connection (2 versions), 1976 (Box 8)
    - Thoughts on future of Christian missions, 1978 (Box 8)
  - Lecture notes
    - Notes for Lyman Beecher Lectures (Box 8)
      Notation of Ellen Gezork indicates that the lectures were never given, due to the illness of the Gezorks' son. The file is arranged in the following order: notes for lectures (from least complete to most complete); notes on books and lectures; clippings on subjects related to the lectures.
- Literary Manuscripts, Series V
  At beginning of this secton is a list of publications "up to 1949" and 1 folder of clippings on miscellaneous topics.
  - Drafts, untitled and undated
    - [Convictions, concerns, commitment];[Christian witness to youth];[Post-war Germany];[Commencement address, Andover Newton];[Commencement address, Rogers Hall School];[I believe ... ];[Revival of Society of Inquiry] (Box 8)
  - Drafts, by title
    - The American student today: observations and reflections (Box 8)
    - American ideals -- Europe's hope (Box 8)
    - The American prospect in religion (Box 8)
    - Chance, fate, or God's will? (Box 8)
    - Crisis (incomplete: pp. 3 and 15) (Box 8)
    - Christianity -- in three words (Box 8)
    - Death is not final (Box 8)
    - A different drummer (Box 8)
    - First things first! (3 versions) (Box 8)
    - The Fate of religion under totalitarianism (Box 8)
    - The Future belongs to freedom (Box 8)
    - God in man's darkness (Box 8)
    - Have no anxiety (Box 9)
    - Historic Baptist distinctives (Box 9)
    - Involved in mankind (Box 9)
    - The Judgments of men -- and of God (Box 9)
    - Notre f oi baptiste (Box 9)
    - Our Baptist faith in the world of today (Box 9)
    - Our witness -- opportunities and perils (Box 9)
    - Religious opposition before the war (Box 9)
    - The Riddle of Providence (Box 9)
    - The Role of the church (report for U.S. Strategic Bombing Survey, Morale Division) (Box 9)
    - This is democracy (Box 9)
    - The Totalitarian state and the individual conscience (Box 9)
    - Toward the renewal of the church (excerpts) (Box 9)
    - The Valley of Baca (Box 9)
    - Wanted -- a fiercer loyalty (2 versions) (Box 9)
    - What Protestantism has contributed to our American heritage (Box 9)
    - Why I am a Baptist (Box 9)
    - Why not the ministry? (Box 9)
  - Drafts, by date
    - 1940 (Box 9)
      July 17 - Chapel talk #1, Northfield Conference of Religious Education; July 20 - Chapel talk #4 July 23 - Chapel talk #6; July 25 - Chapel talk #8
    - 1941 (Box 9)
      From international anarchy to a world community
    - 1942 (Box 9)
      [Review:] A History of Social Thought, by Paul Hanley Furfey; Our strongest weapon: faith; The Stake of religion in a democratic victory; Summary of my statement on: "How long will the war last?"
    - 1944 (Box 9)
      May 23 - Our Christian witness and current problems; July 16 - American ideals - Europe's hope; August (no day given) - The Story of the resistance of the church in Germany to Nazi dictatorship
    - 1948 (Box 9)
      [Review:] The Reconstruction of humanity by Pitirim A. Sorokin; June 8 - Address to the graduating class [Andover Newton]; Oct. 2 - [Review:] The Future of the American Jew by Mordecai M. Kaplan; Oct. 14 - [Review:] A Faith for you, by Brooks Peters Church
    - 1949 (Box 9)
      [Review:] Christianity and Civilisation by Emil Brunner; [Review:] World Christian Handbook by Kenneth G. Grubb; [Review:] Promise and Fulfillment by Arthur Koestler; Palestine is our Business by Millar Burrows (2 versions); [Review:] Religious Liberty by Cecil Northcott
    - 1950 (Box 9)
      Sept. 15 - Report and recommendations, Project E-5073 (12): "Development of social ethics methods and techniques for use in state university faculties ... "
    - 1952 (Box 9)
      The American prospect in religion; Report on the Faith and Order Conference, Lund, August 1952; Dec. 21 - This I know [on Christmas]
    - 1953 (Box 9)
      1953 Germany - key to Europe; Jan. 18 - This I know [on fear]; Feb. 15 - This I know [on opportunity]; Apr. 12 - This I know [on looking beneath surface]; Oct. 25 - [Sermon on Gal. 5:1]
    - 1954 (Box 9)
      March 21 - This I know [on words and deeds]; May 16 - This I know [on discouragement]; Oct. 3 - This I know [on loving our enemies]
    - 1955 (Box 9)
      Our Baptist faith in the world of today; Jan. 2 - Christianity today - advance or retreat?; Feb. 20 - This I know [on forgiveness]; Apr. 17 - This I know [on peace]; May 15 - This I know [on words]; May 21 - Experiencing the reality of God; July 10 - This I know [on the future]; Aug. 7 - This I know [on nature]; Sept. 4 - This I know [on work]; Oct. 2 - This I know [on prayer]; Oct. 30 - This I know [on discipline]
    - 1956 (Box 9)
      March - [Untitled, on National Council of Churches visit to Soviet Union]
    - 1957 (Box 9)
      [Review:] Making ethical decisions by Howard Clark Kee [Review:]; A Faith for the nations by Charles W. Forman
    - 1959 (Box 9)
      [Review:) How to serve God in a Marxist land by Karl Barth and Johannes Hamel
    - 1960 (Box 9)
      [Notes for "Blessed are the peacemakers"]; June 2 - Blessed are the peacemakers (2 versions)
    - 1961 (Box 9)
      Apr. 15 - The Challenge of our declining sense of values
    - 1966 (Box 9)
      Jan. - Building a sermon Jan. - Building a prayer-life; Jan. - Building a church; June - A meditation on time
    - 1968 (Box 9)
      An honest man of God (on Samuel Miller)
    - 1971 (Box 9)
      [Review:] The Right, the good, and the happy by Bernard L. Ramm
    - 1977 (Box 9)
      The Church's vocation in a revolut[ionary] age
  - Book
    - So sah ich die Welt (Box 9)
      (3 folders) Includes draft of a chapter, map, poem by E. Kaestner, offprint of excerpts, reviews, bibliography on Asia
- Class Lectures/Course Documentation, Series VI
  The collection includes material for courses taught at Andover Newton Theological School, Brown University, Furman University, Harvard Divinity School, and Wellesley College.
  - Andover Newton Theological School
    - Christian Ministry I: Field Work Section (Propaedeutics segment on education for the ministry)
      - Class records (Box 9)
        Calendar; List of students for final meetings
      - Lectures (Box 9)
        Introductory lecture; History of theol[ogical] education (including Bible study); Church history; Systematic theology; Practical theology; Christian sociology; Psychology and clinical training; Religious education; Christian-world relations; A Community of Christian scholars; Money matters; Women
    - Church and Labor
      (course taught 1940/41-1949/50)
      - Class records and bibliographies: (Box 9)
        Church and labor (attendance record); Seminar on church and labor (course outline, 2 versions); Reading [Untitled; supplementary reading); Seminar on church and labor: required reading (2 versions); Seminar on church and labor: bibliography; Seminar on church and labor: list of topics (2 versions); Unionism: bibliography; L[abor] in politics; What l[abor] wants?; Labor legislation; Church and labor L[abor]'s attitude toward the church; Labor terms; Church and labor (schedule of student reports)
      - Lectures (Box 9)
        Why do we give a course on Church and Labor?;Labor - Problems; History of l[abor] movement (2 folders); Suggestions for a long-range policy; Suggestions for a time of crisis and conflict; Labor conflict in Newton, Iowa, and the churches; Labor conflict in Gastonia and the churches; Unionism; Union-racketeering; A.F.L. [chart); Labor-union; [Untitled, on unions]; James Myers; After Dobler: Unionism; Prof. Doherty: Prerequisites of collective bargaining; Strike; J. Bryant: Management-labor relationships; Race issues in labor; Labor legislation; Labor in politics; Post-war; Radicalism in U.S. labor; Workers' education; Westphalen: Profit sharing; Ideals for prof[it] sharing; Consumers' cooperatives; New social experiments: profit sharing, cooperatives; Unemployment; Casual-migratory workers; The Effects of unemployment; The Church and labor: the minister's approach to labor; European labor and Christianity; Labor's religious outlook; Roman Catholic Church and labor (attachment: Harold E. Fey, Catholicism and the worker, Christian Century, Dec. 27, 1944)
    - Contemporary Social Problems
      (course taught 1939/40-1949/50)
      - Outlines and bibliographies: (Box 10)
        Contemporary social problems; List for 1945/6 Seminar in contemporary social problems: topics and papers (2 versions); Bibliography for seminar on contemporary social problems (2 versions); Further literature; Guide for the study of American social problems (publisher's release); CSP; Economic planning; Labor-management; Delinquency; Propaganda - freedom of speech - public opinion; Business - monopolies; Bibliography on conservation; Alcoholism as a social problem; Bibliography on housing; Race relations
      - Lecture: C.S.P. (Box 10)
      - Class records (Box 10)
        2nd sem. 1941/42; 2nd sem. 1943/44; [lst sem.] 1945/46; lst sem. 1948/49
      - Clipping: Robert O'Brien, Legalized gambling: Magnet for organized crime (Capital Baptist, June 22, 1978) (Box 10)
    - Contemporary Social Problems -- Alcohol
      - Lectures (Box 10)
        Liquor problem; The Alcohol problem (2 folders); The Alcohol problem (2 pp., Pendle Hill Summer School, 1941); Alcohol
      - Student reports (Box 10)
        Hubert S. Beckwith, The Alcohol problem; Earle Ramsdell, Reading report on alcohol
      - Clippings and pamphlets: (Box 10)
        A.A. [list of meetings]; Help! (Boston Committee for Education on Alcoholism); Vote "Yes" for licenses in Newton (Newton Package Store Dealers' Association); [Special issue on alcoholism] (Social Action, vol. 11, no. 3, Mar. 15, 1945); Herbert Yahraes, Alcoholism is a sickness (Public Affairs pamphlet 118, Public Affairs Committee, 1946); Wilbur La Roe, Jr., [Review of] Claude A. Watson, Repeal has succeeded (no source, 1945?); George M. Gibson, [Review of]; Robert V. Seliger, A Guide on Alcoholism for Social Workers [and] Alcoholics are sick people (no source, 1945?); Temperance (Christian Herald, 1940); S.J. Woolf, The Sick person we call an alcoholic (New York Times Magazine, n.d.); A.E. Caraver, Psychology of the alcoholist (Br. Jour. Med. Psych., vol. 11, part 2, abstract EHK); J. Maurice Trimmer, Sin or sickness? (Christian Century, Oct. 26, 1949)
    - Contemporary Social Problems --Crime and punishment
      - Bibliography: Crime and punishment (Box 10)
      - Lectures (Box 10)
        The Redemption of the criminal (2 pp.); The Redemption of the criminal (14 pp.); The Christian ethic and the crime problem; Capital punishment; What is crime?; Society's relation to crime; Crime and Negroes; Background and causes of crime; Dominant causes of crime; Daniel (on criminology; notes from book?); Baggs, Punishment; Punishment; R. Brown (on punishment and prison reform); Capital punishment; Death penalty (pp. 8-9); Capital punishment; Criminal justice (marked part 3)
      - Pamphlet: Justice? Legalized murder? Read Capital punishment, compiled by Julia E. Johnsen (H.W. Wilson Co., 1939-40) (Box 10)
    - Contemporary Social Problems --Juvenile delinquency
      - Notes of CSP (Box 10)
        Juvenile delinquency; Gable, Juvenile delinquency, 1943/4; McCreary, Juvenile delinquency; Juv. del., Judge Miles, [19]42
    - Cultural and Racial Conflicts
      (course taught 1944/45-1949/50)
      - Lectures and other material, interfiled (Box 10)
        Data; [Untitled; brief outline]; Cultural and racial conflicts (attendance sheet); Topics for termpapers; Examination on cultural and racial conflicts; Bibliography (3 versions); Book reviews; Ten commandments of good will; Groups; Group conflicts (2 folders); The Psychological ladder of prejudice; Christian approach; Group conflicts (5 pp.); [Untitled, on discrimination] ;Can we overcome prejudice?; Quest for racial brotherhood; Prejudice (3 pp.); Prejudice (7 pp.); Psychology of prejudice; Vicious circles; Read on race.. .; Race (3 pp.); Race (1 p. quotations); [Untitled; quotation from Marcel Boule]; Culture and race (p. 2); A Survey of race theories; Classifications on the basis of physical differences (2 folders); The Integration of minorities; Read on Jews.. .; Assigned for reviews; Organizations on Jewish-Christian relations;Milton Steinberg, A Partisan guide to a Jewish problem (outline);William M. Thompson, Preliminary reading report Jews (quotation on index card);Hitler (quotation on index card); Talmud; [Untitled, on idea of a people]; Jews (1 p. on Russia and communism); Christian Jewish relations; Anti-Semitism (2 folders, 18 pp.); Anti-Semitism (2 folders, 14 pp. and appendices); The Anatomy of anti-Semitism; Youth programs on anti-Semitism; A.S.; [Untitled; chart of history of anti-Semitism] ;[Untitled, on Jews and liberalism, p. 1]; [Untitled, on Jews and Reformation]; What should Christians do to combat anti-Semitism?
      - Lectures and other material, interfiled (Box 10)